A Finding Aid to the Alfonso Ossorio Papers, 1949-1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Alfonso Ossorio papers
1949-1985
Archives of American Art
Ossorio, Alfonso, 1916-1990
AAA.ossoalfo
Archival Resource Key
0.7 Linear feet
The papers of painter and assemblage artist Alfonso Ossorio measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1949 to 1985. The papers document Ossorio's career through correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter and assemblage artist Alfonso Ossorio measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1949 to 1985. The papers document Ossorio's career through correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs.
Correspondence consists primarily of letters from Jean Dubuffet and Clyfford Still. Also included are xeroxed letters from Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner. Writings consist of notes and draft manuscripts for the "Fourteen Paintings" exhibition catalog essay, some notes on a list of Pollock artwork, a lecture on Pollock, and a lecture by Dubuffet. Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and posters, exhibition catalogs, and an article on Ossorio. Photographic material consists of photographs of Ossorio and his colleagues, photographs of works of art, exhibitions and opening receptions, and photographs of works by Gregg Blasdel.
Existence and Location of Copies
Materials lent for microfilming on reel 2000 and portions of the collection microfilmed on reel 3888 are available at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Existence and Location of Originals
Letters from Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner are photocopies or transcripts. Location of the originals is unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Filipino American painter and assemblage artist Alfonso Ossorio (1916-1990) was based primarily in the New York area and was a key figure in the Abstract Expressionist and Art Brut movements.
Born in Manila, Philippines, in 1916, Ossorio immigrated to the United States with his family in 1930, settling in the Portsmouth area of Rhode Island and studying fine art at Harvard University and the Rhode Island School of Design. In 1950 Ossorio was commissioned by the parish of St. Joseph in Victorias City, Negros Occidental in the Philippines, to paint a mural which would be known as "The Angry Christ." In the late 1940s Ossorio settled in New York and later purchased the Creeks, an estate in East Hampton where he thereafter spent the majority of his time. From the late 1940s on Ossorio explored abstraction and formed crucial friendships with Jackson Pollock and Jean Dubuffet. In the 1960s he began to create assemblages that he called congregations, and his work was included in numerous exhibitions throughout the United States and elsewhere.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated 1980-1981 by Alfonso A. Ossorio. An addition fron an unknown source was donated in 1985.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1950-1982 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1962-1978 (0.1 linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1949-1985 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-2 OV 3)
Series 4: Photographic Material, 1962-1980 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Alfonso Ossorio conducted by Forrest Selvig, November 19, 1968.
Separated Materials
Material on reel 2000 including correspondence with Thomas Gibson Fine Arts, Ltd., Morris J. Pinto, and Jackson Pollock; correspondence, loan agreements, and clippings concerning Pollock's painting "Lavender Mist"; and cancelled checks, bank statements and other financial material, were returned to Ossorio after microfilming and are not described in the collection Container Inventory.
Latino and Latin American artists; Filipino American artists; Painters -- New York (State); Assemblage artists -- New York (State); Art brut; Abstract expressionism; Still, Clyfford, 1904-1980; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-1985; Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956; Krasner, Lee, 1908-1984
- Correspondence, 1950-1982; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters from Jean Dubuffet and Clyfford Still. Also included are xeroxed letters from Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner.
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1955-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jean Dubuffet, 1960-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clyfford Still, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clyfford Still, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clyfford Still, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clyfford Still, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clyfford Still, 1956-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Xeroxes and Transcripts of Letters from Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner, undated, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Writings, circa 1962-1978; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings consist of notes and draft manuscripts for the "Fourteen Paintings" exhibition catalog essay, some notes on a list of Pollock's artwork, a lecture on Pollock, and a lecture by Dubuffet.
  - For "Fourteen Paintings" Exhibition Catalog, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Gallery Proofs, "Fourteen Paintings" Exhibition Catalog, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Honneur Aux Valeurs Savages" Talk by Dubuffet, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "L'Art Brut" List of Works of Art, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - On Jackson Pollock, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Yale Speech on Jackson Pollock, November 5, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Printed Material, 1949-1985; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and posters, exhibition catalogs, and an article on Ossorio in the The Sunday Times Magazine.
  - Clippings, 1972-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Sunday Times Magazine Article on Ossorio, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Posters, 1951-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Bioscapes" Exhibition Poster, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1949-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - "Fourteen Paintings" Exhibition Catalog, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographic Material, 1962-1980; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographic material consists of photographs of Ossorio and his colleagues, photographs of works of art, photographs of exhibitions and opening receptions, and photographs of works by Gregg Blasdel.
  - Ossorio and Colleagues, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Works of Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Exhibitions and Openings, 1962-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - "Folk Buildings" by Gregg Blasdel, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-8)